Mss.B.G784
American Philosophical Society
John Edward Gray papers, 1783-1884
Mss.B.G784
American Philosophical Society
5.0 Linear feet Ca. 500 items.
These are primarily letters to Gray on various aspects of natural history, with many references to collections at the British Museum of Natural History. There are numerous letters from British scientists and from European colleagues. There are letters from Americans too, such as those from Agassiz which relate to his Florida expeditions and the creation of natural history collections.
Ca. 500 items.
Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875
Box 1-10
Naval History Note
The Gray Papers contain at least one item which may be of interest to naval historians:
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to John Gray. 1853 September 29. Sends chart of the North Atlantic. 2 pages.
Early American History Note
The John Gray Collection contains correspondence, most of which is incoming and addressed to John Gray or his wife. The collection is fairly large and its chronology ranges from the early nineteenth century until the 1880s. Most of the correspondence is to and from Britons, but there is some correspondence from prominent American scientists and natural historians. John Gray was a natural historian active at the British Museum of Natural History, serving from 1840-1874 as keeper of the Zoological Department. MOLE contains a very detailed inventory.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Received and accessioned, 1959. See in-house shelf list for accession dates and numbers.
Biographical/Historical note
John Edward Gray (1800-1875) was an English naturalist and the Keeper of the Zoological Department at the British Museum of Natural History from 1840 until 1874. He endeavored to make the British Museum’s collections “the most extensive, the best known, the best exhibited, the most freely available and only catalogued exhibition of its kind.” Gray attributed his success to “a catholic taste” for all groups of animals. In his lifetime Gray published in excess of eleven hundred papers. His List of Specimens of British Animals in the British Museum (1845) provided an updated list of British fauna. Other major publications included Illustrations of Indian Zoology with General Hardwicke (1832-34) and the privately published Gleanings from the Menagerie and Aviary at Knowsley (1846).
Gray was born in Walsall, Straffordshire on February 12, 1800, the second son of Samuel Frederick Gray, a naturalist and pharmacologist and Elizabeth Forfeit, the daughter of a picture dealer from Convent Garden. After his father got a job with the metallurgist Charles Hatchett, the family moved to London. He had an unorthodox upbringing, since he had no formal education, but was taught to read and write by his parents at home, and generally educated himself by reading the Encyclopedia Britannica. He assisted his father in his Wapping pharmacy, located in borough of London. After the pharmacy failed, he assisted a physician in Shoreditch before finding work in the laboratory of a wholesale chemist. As an adolescent, Gray befriended the entomologist J.F. Stephens, accompanying him on weekend trips into the countryside.
Sometime in 1816 young Gray was also introduced to Dr. William E. Leach, Keeper of the Zoological Department of the British Museum, when it was situated in its first home at Montagu House in Bloomsbury Square. Gaining access through Leach, Gray spent all of his free time as a volunteer, naming and arranging the zoological collections. Through Leach he also gained access to the Museum’s Banksian Library and met other naturalists, who encouraged him to shift his interests from botany to zoology. After Leach’s retirement in 1821, Gray was unsuccessful in his efforts to gain employment as an assistant at the Museum, and worked instead at temporary assignments such as editing the Mechanics Weekly Journal and working briefly with the naturalist illustrator James Sowerby on his great Mineral Conchology of Great Britain.
In his late teens and early twenties Gray assisted his father with several published works, such as Supplement to the Pharmacopoeia (1818) and A Natural Arrangement of British Plants (1821). In the latter work the elder Gray criticized Linnaean system, favoring other European methods of classification instead. The response to the work was quite critical, and the younger Gray, who was responsible for the synoptic portions of the work, developed a very defensive attitude as a result. Gray’s connection with the Natural Arrangement and his failure to mention Sir James E. Smith in a reference to Sowerby’s English Botany were alleged reasons for his exclusion from the Linnean Society to which he applied in 1822.
Gray’s father encouraged him to enter the medical profession, and to this end he attended lectures at St. Bartholomew’s and Middlesex hospitals, at the City Dispensary, and at classes conducted by John Taunton and William Salisbury elsewhere in the city. A revulsion to surgery and a failed application for an assistantship at the British Museum caused Gray to suffer a nervous breakdown in 1822, forcing him to abandon plans for a medical career. Maria Emma Gray, the widow of his cousin Francis Edward Gray and her circle of friends nursed him back to health, and he later married her in 1826.
In December 1824, after assisting John G. Children, the Keeper of the Zoological Collection, with the Museum’s shell collection, Gray was given another temporary assignment, compiling a catalog of reptiles at 15 shillings per day. That year he completed Children’s shell catalog published as the Genera of Shells (which brought its author [Children] the editorship of the Zoological Journal), and published thirty papers. Doubtless, he made himself indispensable to Children, since on May 27, 1837 he was appointed Assistant Keeper and upon Children’s retirement in March 1840, became Keeper. Gray held the position of Keeper of the Zoological Collection for over thirty-four years.
Gray’s goal throughout his tenure in the Zoological Collection, as he mentioned to a select committee on the British Museum in 1836, was to make the Museum’s collections “the most extensive, the best known, the best exhibited, the most freely available and [the] only catalogued exhibition of its kind.” The year he became Keeper, he began the first register of accessions. Afterward, his great interest in the systematics of the catalog led him to produce increasing numbers of publications related to the collections. Gray authored many of the catalogs of mammals himself, such as those on seals, whales, monkeys, lemurs, fruit-eating bats, carnivores, pachyderms, edentates and ruminants. He also wrote catalogs of lizards and shield reptiles [i.e. turtles]. When it appeared in 1845, Gray’s List of the Specimens of British Animals in the British Museum represented an updated list of British fauna. His other important publications included Illustrations of Indian Zoology with General Hardwicke (1832-34) and the privately published Gleanings from the Menagerie and Aviary at Knowsley (1846).
Those who followed Gray as Keeper conceded that the growth of the British Museum’s zoological collections was solely due to his efforts, despite little funding and the opposition of the museum administration. He explained his success in fulfilling his objectives by referring to a “catholic taste” for dealing with every group of animals. He was shrewd and competitive in acquiring multiple reference collections of specimens, among them Gilbertson’s collection of fossils in 1836 and a collection of skins and skeletons of Indian animals from B.H. Hodgson in 1845. One of his competitors was Richard Owen (1804-1892, APS 1845), who was looking for osteological specimens for the Royal College of Surgeons’ Hunterian Museum. However, his contemporaries were not uncritical of his work. Some excused his mistakes as the result of attempts to do too much with too little material, time and assistance. Others blamed a lack of field experience, resulting in “the needless number of genera and species he introduced” which some “thought detrimental to science.” While all of his contemporaries remarked on his incredible energy and enthusiasm, one concluded that “it would have been better, both for zoology and his own future fame, if the outcome... had been represented by half, or even a quarter of the literature under Dr. Gray’s name.”
Gray was a founding member of the Zoological Society in 1826 (and its vice-president from 1865-74). He became a member of the Royal Geographical Society in 1830, a member of the Entomological Society in 1833 (serving as its president in 1858-9), a member of the Botanical Society of London in 1836 (its president, 1836-57) and a member of the Palaeontological Society in 1874. In 1832 Gray was elected to the Royal Society. In 1854 he received an honorary doctorate in Philosophy from the University of Munich.
At the age of sixty Gray’s health began to fail. He suffered a number of mild strokes, and periods of near blindness. In May of 1869 he experienced a paralytic stroke from which he never fully recovered. Nevertheless, he continued in his post as Keeper until December 1874. Gray died on March 7, 1875 and was buried at the churchyard of St. Mary’s in Lewisham.
Gray approached natural history as a collector and organizer of knowledge, but he also realized the limitations of his methods, which focused on the external forms of animals to the neglect of internal structures.
Acland, Henry W., (Henry Wentworth), 1815-1900; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Airy, George Biddell, Sir, 1801-1892; Allman, George James, 1812-1898; Andrews, William, 1802-1880; Babington, Charles Cardale, 1808-1895; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Balard, Antoine-Jérôme, 1802-1876; Bate, C. Spence, (Charles Spence), 1818-1889; Berkeley, M. J., (Miles Joseph), 1803-1889; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de, (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850.; Bland, Thomas, 1809-1885; Bonaparte, Charles Lucian, 1803-1857; Bonomi, Joseph; Bouchard-Chantereaux, Nicolas Robert, 1802-1864; Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850; British Museum (Natural History) -- Natural history collections.; Broderip, William John, 1789-1859; Brookes, Joshua, -- 1754-1821.; Buckland, William, 1784-1856; Busk, George, 1807-1886; Cuming, Hugh, 1791-1865; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895; Du Chaillu, Paul B., (Paul Belloni), 1835-1903; Duméril, C., (Constant), 1774-1860; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867; Fitch, Asa, 1809-1879; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911; Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Isidore, 1805-1861; Geological Society of London; Green, Jacob, 1790-1841; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Hoeven, Jan van der; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874; Lefèvre, Jean-Jacques, 1779-1858; Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851; Müller, Joh., 1801-1858; Nuttall, Thomas, 1786-1859; Pfeiffer, Ludwig Georg Karl, 1805-1877.; Schomburgk, Robert H., Sir, (Robert Hermann), 1804-1865; Société des sciences naturelle de France.; Steenstrup, J. Japetus Sm. -- (Johannes Japetus Sm.), -- 1813-1897.; Valenciennes, M., 1794-1865; Worsaae, Jens Jakob Asmussen, 1821-1885; Assyria -- Antiquities.; Autographs.; Beyond Early America; Florida -- Discovery and exploration.; Geology.; Mollusks.; Natural history -- Catalogs and collections -- England.; Natural history -- Catalogs and collections -- United States.; Nineveh (Extinct city) -- Antiquities.; Shells.
- Papers
  - Statement of account to the Foreign Office, Feb. 27, 1783; 12x7-1/2; Needham, William
    Scope and Contents note
    St. James', D.S.; C. J. Fox and Wm. Needham. 1p.
  - Bill to Lord North for expenses, Oct. 20, 1783; 11-3/4x7-1/2; Smith, John
    Whitehall, D.S.: John Smith, North, and Tho[ma]s Chetham, Clerk. 1p.
  - Warrant to Thomas Boone, March 6, 1788; 12-1/2x8; Carleton, Guy, Lord Dorchester, 1724-1808
    Quebec, Printed D. filled in in ms.: Dorchester, Entered: Thos. Action, and Fran. LeMaistre. 1p. and end.
  - Warrant to Cha[rle]s Crowle, July 6, 1790; 12-3/4x8; Salisbury
    D.S. 1p.
  - Letter to John E. Gray, Dec. 19, 1800, 1850?; 6-1/4x4; Schlagintweit, Adolf von, 1829-1857
    A.L.S. 4p. Refuses invitation.
  - Letter to [Lord Rockingham?], April 4, 1809; 9x7-1/4; Belsham, Thomas, 1750-1829
    Hackney, A.L.in 3rd. P. 2p. and end. by J. E. Gray. Thanks for contribution to Theophilus Lindsay's widow. Describes how fund is to be organized.
  - Letter to ----, March 4, 1811; 9x7; Birkbeck, George, 1776-1841.
    A.L.S. 2p. Will accomodate a profession friend at all times.
  - Prescription for Mrs Gray, 1816 March 18
  - Letter to [John] Edward Gray, 15 February, 1821; James Tandy, Jr.
    Dublin, A.L.S. 3p. Letter accompanying shell specimens collected by Tandy in response to Gray's want list. Difficulties in the study of natural history in Dublin. Mentions Mr. Bulwer, Dr. Coulter?, and Mr. Vigars. Dublin, February ... 1. Bulwer, James. 2. Coulter,. 3. Dublin - Natural history. 4. Vigars,. I. Gray, J[ohn] E[dward], 1800-1875.
  - Epitaph on Prof. Buckland, 1822
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 29, 1824; 8-3/4x8; Rudolphi, Carl Asmund, 1771-1832
    A.L.S. 2p. In German.
    General note
    Unlocated 5/2011
  - Letter to [John E.] Gray, Dec. 5, 1825; 7-1/4x5; Britton, John, 1771-1857
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Asks question.
  - Letter to "Sir John", 1826 August 20; Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875
  - Letter to Mrs. F. Gray, July 17, 1826; 4-1/2x7-1/4; Combe, Taylor, 1774-1826
    A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Fragment. Wishes his remembrances given to friends.
  - Letter to Monsieur Kunth, Paris, Nov. 30, 1826; 6-1/4x4-3/4; Gay-Lussac, Joseph Louis, 1778-1850
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Sends him an address.
  - Letter to J[oh]n Ed[ward] Gray, London, April 10, 1827; 9x7-1/2; Duncan, John Shute, 1769-1844
    Bath, A.L.S. 4p., add. Inexpensive places to stay in Oxford. Concerning P. B. Duncan. Concerning the dodo.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1827 May 27; Owen, William F. W.
  - Letter to Prince Charles Bonaparte, Point Breeze, N.J., Nov. 6, 1827; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Lea, Isaac, 1792-1886
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning a mollusk described and drawn by Gray.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Nov. 23, 1827; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Brookes, Joshua, 1761-1833
    A.L.S. 1p. and end. Concerning a seal's skeleton.
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, London, Feb. 6, 1828; 8x6-1/4; Blainville, Henri Marie Ducrotay, 1777-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Concerning natural history publications.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Aug. 27, 1828; 9x7-1/4; Donovan, Edward, 1768-1837
    A.L.S. 2p. Cannot show exhibits today. Perhaps later he can.
  - Letter to [John] E. Gray, May 9, 1828(?); 8x5; Blainville, Henri Marie Ducrotay, 1777-1850
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Writes a note since Brongniart and Milne-Edwards are visiting England.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1828 May 17; Hennah, W.V.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], March 11, 1829; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Bone, Henry Pierce, 1779-1855
    A.L.S. 1p. Introduces his son, William, who wishes a ticket to the reading rooms of the British Museum.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], April 8, 1829; 8-1/4x7-1/4; Gilbert, Lewis
    A.L.S. 1p. Presents prints to the Museum.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1829 June 12; Lonsdale, W. (William), 1794-1871
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], June 17, 1829; 7-1/2x7-1/4; Bicheno, James Ebenezer, 1785-1851
    A.L.S. 2p. Linnean society will exchange publications.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1829 July 14; Loudon, John Claudius
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1829 December 3; [Jonathan Williams]
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1829? December 22
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1830 March 18; Munden, Joseph Dhepherd
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], March 22, 1830; 7x4-1/2; Buckey, W.
    Weybridge, L. 2p. Concerning publications.
  - Letter to M. Duclos, Paris, March 25, 1830; 10x8; Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875
    London, A.L.S. 2p. on broadside: J. E. Gray. "Proposals for publishing...Illustrations of Indian Zoology..." Concerning mollusks and natural history Refers to Société des sciences naturelle de France and Geological Society of London.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], April 5, 1830; 8-3/4x7-1/4; Dillwyn, Lewis Weston, 1778-1855
    A.L.S. 1p. Introduces J. G. Jeffreys who wishes to see shells.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1830 June 10; McGrigor, John, Sir
  - Letter to [John Thomas] Smith, July 15, 1830; 7x4-1/2; Ellis, Wynne, 1790-1875
  - Letter to ----, Sept. 26, 1830; 4x5; Oken, Laurent, 1779-1851
    A.L.S. 1p. In German.
  - Letter to John Edward Grey (Gray), 1830 October 9; Prattinton, Dr.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1830 November 11; Hayter?, John
  - Letter to J. Smith, March 11, 1831; 7x4-1/2; Beechey, William, Sir, 1753-1839.
    A.L.S. 1p. Introduces John Grace Freeman, who is competent and should draw from marbles in the British museum.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1831 March 18; Upcott, William
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], April 6, 1831; 6-1/4x4-1/2; Bauer
    Kew, A.L. in 3rd. P. 1p. Will be glad to have him examine the microscope.
  - Letter to [John E.] Gray, April 20, 1831; 8x5-1/4; Bouchard-Chantereaux, Nicolas Robert, 1802-1864
    Boulogne, A.L.S. 3p. In French. Thanks for publications. Concerning mollusks.
  - Letter to [Sir John] Richardson, April 29, 1831; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Young, Nicholas
    London, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning cases of specimens and their rough treatment by customs.
  - Letter to J. T. Smith, May 5, 1831; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Chantrey, Francis Legatt, Sir, 1781-1842
    A.L.S. 1p. Recommends a man to study.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1831 June 15; Lindley, John, 1799-1865
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1831 November 18; Walker, N.
  - Letter to J[ohn Thomas] Smith, Jan. 23, 1832; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Beknis, William
    L. 1p. Asks that he let the bearer see some prints.
  - Letter to [John Thomas] Smith, Feb. 2, 1832; 6-1/2 x 4-1/2; Rossi, John Charles Felix, 1762-1839
    A.L.S. 1p. Introduces a man who wishes to study some prints.
  - Letter to the Secretary to the city of London Truss Society, 1832 February 8; Taylor, J. Herbert
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1832 February 13; Maton, William George
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1832 February 19; Haworth, Adrian Hardy
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, April 2, 1832; 9x7-1/2; Buckland, William, 1784-1856
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Asks favor.
  - Pass to the House of Lords, April 13, 1832; 2-3/4x4-3/4; Wellesley, Henry, Baron Cowley, 1773-1847
    A.D.S. 1p.
  - Pass to the House of Lords, April 13, 1832; 2-3/4x4-3/4; Wellesley, Henry, Baron Cowley, 1773-1847
  - Letter to Mrs John Edward Gray, 1832 April 15; Smith, Charles Hamilton
  - Letter to John Thomas Smith, May 29, 1832; 9x7-1/2; Baily, Edward Hodges, 1788-1867
    A.L.S. 1p. Asks that a friend be allowed to sketch in the museum.
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, July 19, 1832; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Coppock, James, 1798-1857
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning an election.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Oct. 13, 1832; 5-1/2x3-1/2; [Farnborough, Charles Long, Baron, 1761-1838
    A.L.S. 1p. Presents prints by Sir J. Reynolds.
  - Letter to J[ohn] T. Smith, Nov. 21, 1832; 7x4-1/2; Etty, William, 1787-1849
    A.L.S. 1p. Introduces a man who would like to study the Elgin marbles.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Nov. 26, 1832; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Bennett, Edward Turner, 1797-1836
    A.L.S. 1p. Asks favor.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Jan. 17, 1833; 9x7-1/2; Chalon, Alfred Edward, 1780-1860
    A.L.S. 1p. Asks that a friend be allowed to study at the Museum.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1833 January 24; Hardwicke, Thomas
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, March 16, 1833; 7x4-1/2; Broderip, W[illiam] J[ohn], 1789-1859
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. Thanks for it, but returns shell.
  - Letter to J. C. Taunton, London, May 19, [1833]; 8x12-3/4; Peel, Robert, 1788-1850
    Fazeley Manor, A.L. in 3rd. P. 1p. and add. Asks for a truss for an old gentleman from the City of London Truss Society.
  - Letter to [Mrs. Maria Emma Gray], May 29, 1833; 7x4-1/2; Christie, Samuel Hunter, 1784-1865
    A.L.S. 2p. Accepts invitation.
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, June 12, 1833; 8x5-1/4; Milne-Edwards, Henri, 1800-1885
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p. Introduces Henri de Sassure and asks that he be encouraged in entomological research.
  - Letter to Mary Ann, July 1, 1833; 10x8; Finch, E.
    Liverpool, A.L.S. 2p. Sends cartoon of politicians.
  - Letter to John George Children, 1833 July 9?; Hay, Robert
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], July 19, 1833; 6-3/4x4-1/2; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843
    A.L.S. 1p. Returns books. Asks for letters of introduction to men in Europe.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Oct. 9, 1833; 9-3/4x8; Green, Jacob, 1790-1841
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Introduces Philip H. Nicklin. Concerning shells.
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, June 23, 1834; 6-1/4x4-3/4; Fox, William Johnson, 1786-1864
    A.L.S. 3p. Asks for his daughter to be admitted to the engraving room.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1835 January 7; Horsfield, Thomas, 1773-1859
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1835 January 21; Sykes, Colonel, (William Henry), 1790-1872
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Sept. 22, 1835; 9-1/2x8-1/4; Olde, E. M.
    Stockholm, A.L.S. 1p. Forwards publications. Difficulty of mailing material to him.
  - Letter to E. J. [sic] Gray, Oct. 26, 1835; 10-3/4x7-1/2; Bonaparte, Charles Lucien Jules Laurent, Prince de Canino, 1803-1857
    A.L.S. 1p. and add.: Lord Dudley Stuart. Concerning his recent publication which he cannot acquire through book-dealers.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1835 December 21; Murray, Hugh
  - Letter to [John E.] Gray, Jan. 22, 1836; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Bennett, Edward Turner, 1797-1836
    A.L.S. 2p. Makes inquiries about publications.
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, Jan. 25, 1836; 9-1/2x8; Tibook
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Thinks an expression of sympathy is enough.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], March 2, 1836; 9x5-1/4; Rudolphi, Carl Asmund, 1771-1832
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. Introduces a friend. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John E.] Gray, April 9, 1836; 7x4-1/4; Children, John George, 1777-1852
    A.L.S. 1p. Confirms appointment.
  - Letter to Dr. [John E.] Gray, May 14, 1836; 7x4-1/2; Panizzi, Anthony, Sir, 1797-1879
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his visit to the museum.
  - Letter to Zoological society of London, June 27, 1836; 10x8; Académie des sciences (France)
    Paris, Printed L. filled in in ms.S: Flourens. 1p. In French. Thanks for Transactions.
  - Letter to John Edw[ar]d Gray, Sept. 9, 1836; 7-1/4x4-3/4; Bell, Thomas, 1792-1880
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Cannot dine with them as planned.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1836 September 24; Macartney, James
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1836? December 22; Sykes, Colonel, (William Henry), 1790-1872
  - Letter to [John E.] Gray, Jan. 22, 1837; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning a shell.
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, Nov. 17, 1837; 7-3/4x5-1/2; Leemans, Conrad, 1809-1893
    Leyden, A.L.S. 2p. Introduces and friend and recommends him.
  - Letter to John Edward Gray, 1838 February 26
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], April 2, 1839; 9x7-1/4; Curtis, Charles M.
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning drawings which Richardson will purchase if it will help the man.
  - Letter to Mrs John Edward Gray, 1839 April 9; Tooke, William
  - Letter to J[ohn] E. Gray, April 22, 1839; 10x8; Cowper, Edward, 1790-1852
    Holborn, A.L.S. 1p. Asks if they would like to hear him lecture on watches, and if not, perhaps the museum would be of interest.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Oct. 13, 1839; 9-1/4x7; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854
    Isle of Man, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning the dredging of the Clyde and how to utilize it for geological and zoological observations. Geology in Scotland, and the formation of lochs.
  - Letter to [John E. Gray], Oct. 23, 1839; 9x7-1/4; Babington, Charles Cardale, 1808-1895